Finding Aid for Bernadine Cimprich papers, 1986-2012
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bernadine Cimprich papers 1986-2012, 1996-2006
Cimprich, Bernadine.
2.5 linear feet
2014122 Aa 2
Bernadine Cimprich was a professor and researcher at the University of Michigan School of Nursing. She conducted extensive research on breast cancer patients and survivors, assessing cognitive issues during treatment, survivorship and quality of life, and the role of environment on patient recovery. The collection consists of materials relating to her teaching, research and service.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were received form Bernadine Cimprich in 2012 (Donor no. 10755 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Bernadine Cimprich earned a nursing diploma in 1960 from the St. Francis School of Nursing in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. She worked for several years at the St. Francis General Hospital before becoming part of the staff at the Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, in New York, New York in 1963. It was in this hospital that she worked more actively in the areas of education and cancer through different roles, such as Clinical Instructor and Coordinator for Patient Education, after completing a B.S. in Nursing at Columbia University's Teachers College in 1967 and an M.A. degree from the same institution in 1977. Afterwards, Cimprich pursued a PhD at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor where her research focused on fatigue and cognition in cancer patients. She completed her degree in 1990 with her dissertation Attentional Fatigue and Restoration on Individuals with Cancer.
Cimprich went on to teach as a School of Nursing faculty member at the University of Wisconsin in Madison from 1990 to 1993 before she joined the faculty at the University of Michigan as an assistant professor and later as an associate professor in 2000 when she received tenure. She taught courses at all academic levels. Several of her graduate courses were on topics related to research and nursing science, bio behavior and functions, as well as the role of the environment in patient care. At the University of Michigan, Cimprich actively worked on committees and administrative services, for the University and the School of Nursing, in the areas of admission, grant preparation, search committees, Institutional Review Board, planning and several task force groups.
Cimprich is known for her extensive research work on cancer patients and cancer survivors, with a special attention on breast cancer patients. Her studies focused on cognitive problems during treatment, survivorship and quality of life, and the role of environment on patient recovery. She was the Principal Investigator and Co-Principal Investigator on multiple projects with the University of Michigan Comprehensive Cancer Center, the Walther Cancer Center, the National Cancer Institute, Michigan State University, UM School of Nursing, and the University of Wisconsin.
Her work and achievements were recognized through awards and appointments such as her fellowship into the American Academy of Nursing in 2001, and through various other teaching and research awards. Cimprich was also Senior Scientist for the Behavioral Cooperative Oncology Group, a member of the Council for the Advancement of Nursing Science, a member of the Oncology Nursing Society, as well as a member of multiple professional associations. In January 2012 Cimprich was named Associate Professor Emerita of Nursing.
--------------------------------
Sources consulted:
Bernadine Cimprich papers --Personal series - Curriculum Vitae
Bernadine Cimprich papers --Personal series - Emeritus Appointment
The Bernadine Cimprich papers (2.5 linear feet) document her work primarily with the University of Michigan. The papers span from 1986 to 2012. The contents are for the most part paper materials which include numerous research proposals, IRB documentation, pilot studies and course materials. The contents are divided into four series: Personal, Service, Teaching, and Research.
Subjects:
Breast--Cancer--Nursing--Michigan.; Breast--Cancer--Research.; Cancer--Patients.; Cimprich, Bernadine.; Nursing--Research--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Oncology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing.
- Personal 1999-2012
  The Personal series (1999- 2012) includes documents relating to Cimprich's professional achievements, appointment, tenure, fellowships, and her Curriculum Vitae. The contents are arranged alphabetically.
  - Curriculum Vitae 2012 (Box 1)
  - Emeritus Appointment 2011 (Box 1)
  - Fellowship into American Academy of Nursing 2001 (Box 1)
  - Tenure Packet -- University of Michigan 1999 (Box 1)
- Service 1993-2008
  The Service series (1993 - 2008) documents Bernadine Cimprich's work with professional organizations and cancer research related efforts not specifically tied to the University of Michigan. The series is arranged chronologically.
  - Nursing Oncology Research Program (UM Cancer Center) 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Cancer Center 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Behavioral Oncology 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Breast Cancer and Aging Retreat 1996 (Box 1)
  - Cancer Prevention and Control Group 1997-1999 (Box 1)
  - WISE Wisdom in Service to Education Task Force 1996, 2005, 2006 (Box 1)
  - National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) Fatigue Guidelines 2002 (Box 1)
  - Oncology Nursing Foundation Institute 2008 (Box 1)
  - Behavioral Cooperative Oncology Group (BCOG) of the Walther Cancer Institute 2008 (Box 1)
  - Center for Enhancement and Restoration of Cognitive Function (CERCF) (Box 1)
- Teaching 1996-2011
  The Teaching series (1996 - 2011) contains course and lecture materials on courses designed or taught by Cimprich at the University of Michigan. Materials on lectures given elsewhere are also included. These are arranged by course level number.
  - Nursing 258 (Box 1)
  - Nursing 295 Honors Seminar (Box 1)
  - Nursing 446 Nursing Therapies 1996 (Box 1)
  - Nursing 505 Bio Behavior I 2003-2007 (Box 1)
  - Nursing 532 Theoretical Base for Advanced Nursing Practice (Box 1)
  - Nursing 622 Informational Therapies 1997, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Nursing 622 Environmental Therapies 2006 (Box 1)
  - Nursing 831Design, Methods and Analysis II 2005, 2006, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Nursing 869 Human Responses and Altered Biological Function 1995, 1997, 1998, 2001, 2003 (Box 1)
  - Nursing 870/873 Biological and Psychological Foundations of Cognition 2010, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Nursing 874/N887 Enhancing and Restoring Cognitive Function through Environment 1997, 1999, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Pain Lectures (Box 1)
- Research 1986-2011
  The Research series (1986 - 2011) documents her extensive research on patients with breast cancer, cognitive functions, pain, cancer survivor quality of life, and the role of environment in the restorative process. Contents include multiple research proposals, and research related materials. Two video tapes with features on her research are included. The series is arranged chronologically following the time frames for the research projects, which often overlap. A subseries of publications is included at the end arranged in chronological order.
  - NSRA Proposal and grant-- Optimizing cognitive Functions in Patients with Cancer 1986, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Video Material 1996 (VHS format)
    - A Dose of Mother Nature: Good medicine for Cancer? University of Michigan Medical Center Broadcast Network (Box 1)
    - Bernadine Cimprich Research Project. Channel 4. 11pm News 1996 (Box 1)
  - R29: Nursing Therapy: Attentional Fatigue in Cancer Patients 1995
    - Proposal (Box 1)
    - Progress Report (Box 1)
    - Budget Awards (Box 1)
    - Institutional Review Board (Box 1)
    - Intervention (Box 2)
    - Application Resubmission, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Family Home Care for Cancer, 1996-97 2001
    - Proposal and IRB 1996-1997, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Analysis and Appendices (Box 2)
    - Report 2001 (Box 2)
  - Fatigue and Functional Outcomes in Elderly Breast Cancer 1994, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Psychosocial Quality of Life and Related Service Needs in Survivors of Breast Cancer 1997-2005 (Box 2)
  - Taking Charge
    - Pilot 2001 (Box 2)
    - Proposal 2000-2001, 2008 (Box 2)
    - Protocol Review 2001 (Box 2)
    - Institutional Review Board (Box 2)
    - Data and Safety Monitoring (Box 2)
    - Project Summary (Box 2)
  - Taking Charge Sessions: Health Educators Manual and Patient Workbook
    - Session 1 (Box 2)
    - Session 2 (Box 2)
    - Session 3 (Box 2)
    - Session 4 (Box 2)
    - Workbook Original (Box 3)
  - African-American Women with Breast Cancer
    - Proposal 2005 (Box 3)
    - Focus Group Findings 2005 (Box 3)
  - Altered Brain Function in Breast Cancer (fMRI)
    - Pilot Study 2003-2004 (Box 3)
    - R01 Proposal and Grant Application 2006 (Box 3)
  - Publications, 2 folders
    - 1992-2004 (Box 3)
    - 2005-2011 (Box 3)